I do apologize for the
for the Euro BSD Con slide. I've redone the
title page and redone the
and made some changes to the slides
and they didn't make it for approval
by this afternoon so
okay so
I'm gonna be talking about
doing
about isolating jobs for performance and predictability
in clusters
before I get into that
I want to talk a little bit about
who we are and
what our problem space is like because that
%uh a dictates that that %uh has an effect
are solutions base
I work for the aerospace corporation
%uh we we work
we operate a federally-funded
research and development center
%uh in the area national security space
and in particular we work with the air force
space and missile command
and with that the national reconnaissance
office
and our engineers support a wide variety
of activities within that area
so we have
a bit over fourteen hundred to correct
sorry twenty four hundred engineers
in virtually every discipline we have
as you would expect we have our rocket scientists
we have people who build satellites
we have people who build sensors that go on
satellites people who study this sort of things
that you
see when you
use those sensors
that sort of thing
we also have civil engineers and
electronic engineers
and process
computer process people
so we literally do everything related to space
and all sorts of things that you might not
expect to be related to space
because we also for instance help build ground
systems since satellites arent very useful if
there isn't anything to talk to them
%um
and these engineers
since they're solving all these different problems we have
engineering applications in you know
virtually every size you can think of
ranging from you know little spreadsheet things that
you might not think of as an engineering
application but they are
to Matlab programs or want to see code
or one of traditional parallel for us
serial code
and then
large parallel applications either in house
or genetic algorithms and that sort
of thing
or traditional
the classic parallel code
like you work around a crater or something material simulation
%uh or %uh
or that or food flow
or that sort of thing
so
so we have this big application space
just want to give a little introduction to that because
it
does come back and influence what we
the sort of solutions we work at
so the rest of the talk Im gonna talk about oops
we skipped a slide, There we are. Thats a little better
what I'm interested in is I do high
performance computing
at company
and I provide high performance computing resources
to our users
as part of my role in our technical
computing services organization
so
our primary resource at this point is
the fellowship cluster
it's a for the
named for the fellowship the ring
it's the
we're gonna wrap some nodes
wrap the core systems
%uh over here there's a
Cisco a large Cisco switch. Actually today
there are around two sixty five oh nines if
you assess them
and because we couldnt get the core density otherwise
and primarily the Gigabit Ethernet system runs
FreeBSD currently 6.0 because we havent upgraded
it yet
planning to move to probably to 7.1
maybe slightly past 7.1
%uh if we want to get the latest initial APM changes in
we use the Sun Grid Engine scheduler was one of
the two main options for open source
resource managers on cluster the other one being
that
the %uh
Torp
and now the combination from cluster resources
so we also have
that's actually
40 TB thats really the raw number on a sun thumper and
and
that thirty two usable once you start using ---- two
since you might actually like to have your data
should a disk fail
and with today's discs drade
grade five
doesn't really cut it
%um
we also have some other resources coming on but Im going to be
two smaller clusters unfortunately probably running Sun x and
some SMPs but
Im going to be concentrating here on the work we're
doing on our other
our FreeBSD based cluster
first of all
first of all I want to talk about why we want to
share resources. Should be fairly obvious
but I'll talk about it in a little bit
and then what goes wrong when you start sharing resources
after that I'll talk about some different solutions
to those problems
and
some fairly trivial experiments that we've done
so far in terms of the it's enghancing the schedule or
using operating system features
so you mitigate those problems
%um
and %uh
then conclude with some future work
obviously if you have a resource the size
of the size of our cluster fourteen hundred
cores roughly
you probably want to share it unless you
purpose built it for a single application
you're going to want to have your users
sharing it
and you don't want to just say you know you get on Monday
probably not going to be a very effective
option
especially not when we have as many uses we
do
we also can't just afford to buy another one
every time a user shows up
so one of our
senior VPs said a while back
you know
we could probably afford to buy just about
anything we could need once
we can't just
buy ten of them though
if you really really needed it
dropping
small numbers of millions of dollars on
computing resources wouldnt be
impossible
but we can't go to you know just have every engineer
who wants one just call Dell and say ship me ten racks
it's not going to work
and the other thing is that we cant
we need to also provide quick turnaround
for some users
so we can't have one user hogging the system and
hogging it until they are done
because we have some users
n then the next one can run
because we have some users who'll
come in and say well I need to run
for three months
and
we've had users come in and literally run
pretty much using the entire system for three months
well so we've had to provide some ability for other
users to still get their work done
so we can't just.. so we do have to have some share
however when you start to share any resource
like this
you start getting contention
users need the same thing at the same time
and so they fight back and forth for it and they
can't get what they want
so you have to balance them a bit
%um
you know also
%uh some jobs lie when they
request resources and they actually need
more than they ask for
which can cause problems
so we schedule them. We say you're going to fit
here fine and they run off and use
more than they said
and if we don't have a mechanism to constrain
them
we have problems
%uh likewise
once these users start to contend
that doesn't just result in
the jobs taking
taking longer in terms of wall clock time
because they are extremely slow
but there's overhead related to that contention
because they get swapped out due to to that pressure on
on
on various systems
if you really
for instance run put of memory then you go into
swap and you end up wasting all your cycles
pulling junk in and out of disc
wasting your bandwidth on that
so there are
resource
there are resource cost to the contention not merely
a delay in returning results
so now I'm going to switch gears and start talk so I'm
going to talk a little bit about different
solutions to these
to the
these contention issues
and %uh
%uh and and look at different ways of solving the
problem.most of these are things that have
already been done
but I just want to talk about
the different ways and then
evaluate them in our context
so a classic solution to the problem is
Gang scheduling
it's basically conventional Unex process
context switching
written really big
you what you do is you have your parallel
job thats running
on a system
and it runs for a while
and then after a certain amount of time you basically
shove it all you kick it off of all the nodes
and let the next one come in
and typically when people do this they do it on
on the order of hours because the context switch
time is extremely large is extremely high
for example
because it's not just like swapping a process
internet. You suddenly have to co-ordinate
the this context which across to all your processes
if you're running say
MPI over TCP
you actually need to tear down the TCP sessions
because you can't just have TCP timers sitting
around
or that sort of thing so
there there's a there's a lot of overhead
associated with this.You take a long context switch
if all of your infrastructure supports this
it's fairly effective
and it does allow jobs to avoid interfering
with each other which is nice
so you can't you don't have issues
because you're typically allocating
whole swaps of the system
and for properly written applications
partial results can be returned which for some of
our users is really important where you're doing a
refinement
users would want to look at the results and
say okay
you know is this just going off into the weeds
or does it look like it's actually converging on
some sort of useful solution
as they don't want to just wait till the end
down side of course is that this context
switches costs are very high
and most importantly there's really a lack
of useful implementations
a number of platforms have implemented this in the past
but in practice on modern clusters which are
built on commodity hardware
with you know
communication libraries written on standard protocols
the tools just arent there
and so
it's not very practical
also it doesn't really make a lot of sense with small jobs
and one of the things that we found is we have users who have
embarrassingly parallel problems for they need to look at
you know twenty thousand studies
and they could write something that looked more like a
conventional parallel application where they
you know wrote a schedule and set up an MPI a Message Pasting Interface
and handed out tasks to pieces of their job and then you
could do this
but then they would be running a schedule and they would
probably do a bad job of it turns out it's actually
fairly difficult to do right
even a trivial case
and so what they do instead is they just select twenty
twenty thousand jobs to great and say okay
whatever I'll deal with it
earlier versions that might have been a problem
current versions of the code
handle easily a million jobs that
so not really a big deal
but those sort of users wouldn't fit well
into the gang scheduled environment
at least not in a
conventional gang scheduled environment where
you do gang scheduling on the regularity of
jobs
so from that perspective it wouldnt work very well
if you have all the pieces in place and you are
doing a big parallel applications it in fact
an extremely effective approach
another option which is sort of related
it's in fact
take taking an even course with regularity
is single application or single project
clusters or sub-clusters
%uh for instance this is used some national labs
where you're given a cycle allocation for a
year based on your grant proposals
and what your cycle allocation actually comes to you as is
here's your cluster
here's a fun-ed
here's this chunk of notes. they're yours. Go to it
Install your own OS. Whatever you want
it's yours
and then and at a sort of finer scale there's things such as
you could use Emulab
which is the network emulation system but also does a less install and configuration
so you could do dynamic allocation that way
Sun's
Project Hedeby now actually I think it's
called service domain manager
is the product size version
or some Clusters on Demand
they were actually talking about web hosting clusters but
things that allow rapid deployment unless you
do that a little
little
a more granular level than the
the allocate them once a year approach
none the less
lets you give people whole clusters to work with
nice one nice thing about it is
the at the isolation between the processes
is complete
so you dont have to worry about users stomping on each other.
Its their own system. they can trash it all they
want
if they flood the network or they
run the nodes into swap
well that's their problem
but it also has the advantage that you can tailor the the images
on the nodes of the operative systems to
meet the exact needs of the application
down side of course is its course
theres a system whichgranularity. in our environment that doesn't work
very well
since we do have all of these all these different types of jobs
context switches are also pretty expensive. certainly on the order of minutes
Emulab typically claim something like ten minutes
there are some systems out there
for instance if you use I think its open boot that
they're calling it today. It used to be 1xBIOS
where you can actually deploy a system in
tens of seconds
mostly by getting rid of all that junk the BIOS writers wrote
and
the OS speed is pretty fast if you dont have all
that stuff to waylay you not
but in practice on sort of
on the shelf
the context switches time quite high
users of course can interfere with themselves
you can argue it's not a problem but
ideally you would like to prevent
that
one of the things that I have to deal with
is that my users are
almost universally
not trained as computer scientists are programmes
you know there's there's really no domain
area
they're really good in that area
their concepts of the way hardware works in the
way software works
dont match reality in many cases
its pretty rare in practice
well I've heard one one lab that does it significantly
but it's like they do it on sort of a yearly
allocation basis
and throw the hardware away after two or three years
and you do typically have some sort of the deployment
system in place
or in most types of cases actually
usually your application comes with
and here's what we're going to spend on this many people
on this project so this is
big resource allocation
and %uh yet and I guess one other issue with this is there's no real easy
way to capture on underutilized resources
for example
if you have
an application which you know say single-threaded
and uses a ton of memory
on and is running on a machine
the machines we're buying these days are eight core so
thats wasting a lot of CPU cycles you're just
generating a lot of heat doing nothing
so ideally you would like a scheduler that
said okay so you're using
using eight or seven of the eight Gigabytes of
RAM but we've got these jobs
sitting here that
need next to know need
a hundred megabytes so we swap seven of
those in along with the big job
and backfill and in this
mechanism there's no
there's no good way to do that
obviously if the users have that application
next they can do it themselves
it's not something where we can be easily
bring in
bring in more jobs and have a mix to
take advantage of the different
resources
a related approach is to
to install virtualization software on the
equipment and this is this is
a
this is the essence of
what Cloud computing is at the moment
it's Amazon providing Zen
Zen hosting for
relatively arbitrary yet
OS images
it does have advantage that allows rapid deployment
in theory if your application is scaleable provides for
extremely high scaleability
particularly if you
arent us and therefore can possibly somebody else's hardware
in in our application's face thats
not very practical so
we can't do that
and
it also has the advantage that you can run
you can have people with their own image in there
which is tightly resource constrained but you
can run more than one of them on it. but no for instance
you can give
one job
four cores and another job two cores another
you know and have a couple single core
jobs in theory
you can get fairly strong isolation there
obviously there are shared resources underneath
and you
probably can't
afford to completely isolate say network bandwidth
at the bottom layer
you can be some but
if you go overboard you can spend all your time on accounting
you also can again
tailor the images to the job
and in this environment actually you can
do that even more strongly than that
the sub-cluster approach
in that you can often do run
a five-year-old operating system or ten-year-old
operating system if you're using full virtualization
and that can allow
allow obsolete core with your baseline core which is
important in our space because
the average program runs ten years or more
our average project runs ten years or more
and as a result
you might have to go rerun this program that was written
way back on
some ancient version of windows or whatever
it also does provide
the ability to recover resources
as I was talking about before
%uh but you can't do easily with sub-clusters because you cant just slip
another image
on the on there and say are you can use anything and
you know get that image ideal priority essentially
down side of course is that it is in complete
isolation and that there is a shared
hardware
you're not likely to find I don't think
any the virtualization systems out there
right now
virtualize
your segment of
memory bandwidth
or your segment
of cache
of cache base
so users can in fact interfere with themselves and each other in this
environment
it's also
%uh not really efficient for small jobs from the cost of running an
entire arrest for every
job is fairly high
even with
relatively light
%uh you know it's like OS is you're still looking
couple hundred megabytes in practice
once you get everything up and running unless you get totally stripped
down
and %uh
theres significant overhead
theres CPU slowdown typically in the
you know typical estimates are in the twenty
percent range
numbers really range from fifty percent to
five percent depending on what exactly you're doing
possibly even lower
or higher
and and just
you know the overhead because you have the whole OS there's a lot of a lot
of duplicate
stuff
the various vendors
have their answers they claim you know we can
we can merge that and say oh you're running the same kernel so we'll keep your memory
we use the same memory but
at some level
it's all going to get duplicated
a related option
comes from sort of the the internet havesting
industry which is to use virtual private
which is the technology from virtual private servers
the example that everyone here is probably familiar with is jails where
you can provide
your own file system root
your network interface
and what not
and
the nice thing about this is
that unlike full virtualization
the overhead is very small
basically costs you
an entry in your process table
or an entry in few structures
there's some extra tests in their kernel but otherwise
there's there's not a huge overhead for virtualization you don't need
an extra kernel for every
image
so you get you get the difference here
between
be able to run maybe
you might be able to squeeze two hundred VMR images onto a machine
VMR people say no no don't do that but we have machines that are running
nearly that many
they're what
on the other hand there are people out there on thousands of
virtual hosts
using this technique at a single machine so
big difference in resource use
on especially with light
in the lightly loaded use
in our environment we're looking more running a very small number of them but still
that overhead is significant
you still do have some ability to tailor the
images to jobs needs
you could have a
custom root that for instance you could be running
FreeBSD x6 in one
in one
virtual server and seven in another
you have to be running of course seven kernel or eight kernel to make
that work
but it allows you to do that
we also in principle can do
evil things like our sixty four-bit kernel and then thirty two bit
user spaces because
say you have applications that you can't find the source to do anymore
or wide worst wide worries you don't
have the source to any more
an answer
interesting things there
and the other nice thing is since you're
you're doing a very lightweight and incomplete
virtualization
you don't have to virtualize things you don't
care about so you dont have the overhead of
virtualizing everything
downsides of course are incomplete isolation
you are running processes that on the same kernel
and they can interfere with each other
and there's dubious flexibility obviously
I don't think anybody
should have the ability to run Windows in a jail
theres some
Net BSD peak of support but
and I dont think it's really gotten to that point
one one final area
that sort of diverges from this
is the classic
Unix solution to the problem
on this on single
in a single machines
which is
to use existing resource limits and resource partitioning techniques
you know for example all Unix like our Unix systems have to process
resource limits
a resource and typically
schedule a
cluster schedulers support the common ones
so you can set a
memory limit on your process or a CPU time limit on your process
and the schedulers typically provide
at least
lot of support for
the limits on
a given set of process. thats part of the job
also the most
you know there are a number of forms of research
partitioning that
are available as
the in that
as the standard feature
on so memory discs are one of them so
if you want to create a file system space it's
limited in size. Create a memory disc
and back it
and back it with a --- file
Quotas another mechanism
of partitioning that
disc use
and then there are techniques like CPU affinities that you can walk
processes to it
a single process
processor a set of processors
and so they can't interfere with each other
with processes running on other processes
the nice thing about this first is that you're using existing
facilities so you dont have to rewrite
also new features
for each application
and they tend to integrate well with existing schedulers
in many cases
parts of them are already implemented
and in fact the experiments that we'll talk about this later are using
this type of
technique
cons are of course
incomplete isolation again
and theres typically no unified framework
for the concept of a job when it comes to the center process
yeah there there are a number of data structures within the kernel for
instance the session
which
certain aggregate processes
but there isnt one
in
in BVSD at this point
allows you to place resource limits on this in a way that you can process
--- did have support like that
where they have a job ID
and there could be a job limit
and slurs projects
pursue similar not not quite the same
processes or part of a project but
it's not quite the same inherited relationship
and typically
there arent
limits on things like badwidth. there was
a sort of a
bandwidth limiting
nice type interface
on that I saw
first thing as a research project
many years ago I think it was that stage
where you could say this process can have
you know five megabits
or or whatever
but I haven't really seen anything take off
that would be a pretty neat thing to have
but one other exception there
is on Irex again
the XFS file system supported guaranteed data rates on file handles
you could say
you know if you would say I need
ten megabits read or ten megabits write
whatever you say
okay and go
and and then you could read and write and
it would do evil things file system
in some cases
all to making sure that you could get that terrific data rate
by
by keeping the file
so now Im going to talk about what we've done
what we needed was the solution to handle
a wide range of job types
so all the options we looked at for instance
single application clusters of
project clusters
I think that the isolation they
provide is essentially unparalleled
and in our environment we probably have to
virtualize in order to be
efficient in terms of
being able to handle our job nix and what not to handle
the fact that our users
tend to have
spikes in their in their use
on a on a large scale so for instance we get those that show and say
that they need to run for a month
on and then
some indeterminate number of months later
they'll do it again
for that sort of quick
demands
we really need the virtuals something
virtualized
and then we got to pay the price of %uh
of the overhead
and again it doesn't handle small jobs and that is a
large portion of our job nix and
of that
quarter million or something jobs line
on our cluster
%uh I would guess that
more than half of those were submitted
in
batches of more than ten thousand
so they'll just pop up
the other method to have looked at
are up
were using resource limits
the nice thing of course is they're achievable
with
they acheive useful isolation
and the inflexible with under existing functionality or small
extension so that's what we think
concentrating on
also been doing some thinking about
could we use the techniques there
and combine them with jails
or related features
it may be bulking up jails to be more like ------
or containers I think they're calling this
week
and
so we're looking that
to be able to provide
to to to be able to provide pretty user operating environments
potentially isolating users from operating suffrance as we upgrade the kernel
and users can continue using it all the
images they don't have time to rebuild their
application in
and handle the updates in libraries and what not
they also have potential to provide strong isolation for security
purposes
%uh which could be useful in the future
we do think that that
of of its to of these of these mechanisms the nice thing is that
resource limit
the resource limits and partitioning scheme
as well as virtual private service are very
similar imitation requirements
set up a fair bit more expensive
in the VPS case
while nonetheless they're fairly similar
what we've been doing is we've taken Sun Grid Engine we've taken Sun
Grid Engine
and we were originally intended to actually
extend Sun Grid Engine and modify its demands
to do work
on what we ended up doing instead is realize
that well
we can actually starts flying alternate program
to run instead of the shepherd
The shepherd is the process
that starts all
starts the the script that
can reach job
on a given node
it collects usage and forwards signals to the
children
and also is responsible for starting remote
components
so shepherd is started and then
traditionally in seperate engine it starts out
it's own --the event
and
jobs connect over
these days that for their own
you're a mechanism which is
secure
not using the
arch old code
on
so what we've done is we've implemented a rapid script
which allows a pre-command hook
to run before the shepherd starts
the command rapper send before we send shepherd before we can run like the N program
or the week and why not
troops or whatever
to set up the environment that it runs in or CPU
that will show later
on and I first met her for cleanup
simply move because I felt like it
the first thing we implemented is memory backs temporary directors. the motivation for
this
is that
we've had problems for users will you know
run slash ten on the nodes
where we have the figures is that they do have discs
and most of the disc is available as slash ten
we had some cases
particularly early on where users would fill the discs and not complete it
their job would crash and they wold forget to add clean up code or whatever
other jobs would fail strangely
you might expect that you just get a you would get a nice error message
being programmers
people would not
handle very correctly
now of course you have issues like for instance
the PDL library
unexpectedly fails and reports a completely strange error
if it can't create a file to have
because it needs to create an extra file in itself
so what we've done here
is it turns out that Sun Grid Engine actually creates a temporary
directory often the
typically but you can change
that
I think it's that's a
location
we educated most of all users now
to use that location correctly and values
that very cool
they treat their files understand her
and then when the job exits
the Grid Engine deletes the temp dir
and that all gets cleaned up
the problem of course being that of multiples
also warning on the same note same time
one of them could still fill temp
so the solution was pretty simple
we created a
rapper script at the beginning of the job
creates a
a
memory file to swap back to MB file system
of a user requestable size of the default
and
this has a number of advantages the biggest one of course is that
it's their fixed size so we get
you know
the user gets
what they asked for
and once they run of space, they run out of space well
and too bad they ran out of space
they should have asked for more
the other
the other advantage is the side-effect that
now that we're running swap back memory files systems for temp
the users who only use a fairly small amount of temp
should see vastly improved performance
because they're running in memory
rather than writing to disc
quick example
we've a little job script herel
prints chapter and
prints the
amount of space
we consider job request saying that we want
this is what we want hundred megabytes of
temp space
the same that's why if this
so the program doesn't
so the program ends at the end of it
%uh for doing it
heres a live demo
all and then
you look at the output
you can see it
does in fact it creates a memory file system
I attempted to do as great code
having a variable space that
having a variable space that is roughly what user asked for
the version I had
when I was attempting this was not entirely
accurate
trying to guess what all the
USFS overhead would be
as the result was
%uh not quite consistent
I couldn't figure out easy function so
it does a better job than it did to start with
sometimes however
today that that's a good case
we're coming to it
deployed pretty soon
it's pretty easily
well sometimes it's not enough
the biggest issue is that they were badly designed programs all
all over the world
don't you step to like they're supposed to
in fact
so there are all these applications
there are a lot about patience still that need
ten because they'll still need start up
that sort of thing
so
all
so we have problems with these
realistically
we cant change all of them
it's just not going to happen
so we still have a lot of people
running out resources
%uh so we probably
feel that
was general solution is right a per job slash temp
the first was that her from the files system
at its best
we think there is some ways to me that
and so he said okay let's give it a shot
just to inter these concepts for people who are unfamiliar with him
offering someone services recent ones that
contained rules
Richard Senator long time
angeles half past be different for different
processes
for example
you create the files
on create
they ask someone whose contents are
this veritable which has a the fall not shells
fell the fall diet
and you
he didn't get different results with different
variables that
what about her the implementation we've got
it's drive from grateful and mission was to
the data structures are gonna call
authorities a number of changes
the biggest one is that the two the concept
of us troops and returned them entirely around
he added that
in trade as one of his assistants the which
is over overridden by the users scope and by a
progressive scope
problem with that is if you
only think about say the systems scope
and
you decide you want to do something clever like have
root file system which
%uh
were slashed with points the different things
for different %uh
different architectures
were seriously until the users come along
and
they're upset there are variable
up for you
if you have CSX like the program and you don't
defensively
and you don't implement correctly
the obvious that they sat obviously you would
Richard riordan often that I believe they
did
there's a whole class of problems where
it's easy to screw up
add and do something wrong there
so by
reversing the order
we can't we can reduce the risks
at the moment we don't
haven't you sir
I just don't like the idea of the users scope
to be honest
from being they see you dont have to have
poor user
that just sits around forever
you can never guard elected accepted the strain
of late
just doesn't seem like a great idea to me
on it
just hasn't been implemented
because it wasn't entirely clear as to what the semantics should be
i also
I also added default variable support variable
also shell style
for
to some extent undoes the scope
the scope change
in that
the default variable becomes a system scope
which is overridden by everything
but there are cases where we need to do that
in particular who wants implement their
slashed temp which varies
we have to do something like this because the temp needs to work
if
if we don't have the job values set
I also decided to use
percent instead of dollar signs to avoid
confusion over shell variables because these
are
a separate namespace in the kernel
can't do it in a nice to do all the evaluation in the
user space
it's classic vulnerability
the that in the database for instance
and when I was in the past and avoid confusion
with but yet that's and worthy and for the
now BST implementation
first is not allowed
he's a reduced rate of one set of core values
that will be enough ballots for
on I don't have any automated variables such
as the %uh
the process is not you which is universally
sat and that he is the implementation war
on
aids
hey I do i'd be very foolish they also have
and currently and it allows Senator
setting about using other processes yourself
in your own insurance
that may change but it's a
one of my goals here is because they were
subtle ways to make no mistakes and
cause securities undergo days
I I've attempted to storm the features that
down to the point where you
at some reasonable chance of not
doing that
if you start building systems on the for
the final area that we've worked on
he is moving away from the final system states
and the NCR see these sets of them
chuck roberts indictment alleges a out for
them out
people may I see he said functionality which
allows you to
but it also seems the issues that have been
set
the affinity of that
see he said
political observers also stopped in on this
and on a CD set was it was stuffed in the
one that was created by this
in an apparent
so what I hear
it's here unless you can figure issue
every day has won so what
first you here
there there are a number of other ways you
can configure basically us lost is something
in jobs and money
%uh federal jobs crosses what's going to happen
would be more than one swatch
pop quizzes making the applications where
persons who tends to spend a fair bit of time
waiting for Iran
you are looking at more than one slot per CPU so two slots per
CPU is not uncommon
but probably the most common configuration
and the one that
you get out of the box is you just install a Grid Engine
wants free CPU
and that's how that's how we run because we
want users to have
that whole CPU for whatever they want to do with
it
So drums are allocated one or more slots
if they're
depending on whether they're sequential or parallel jobs
and how many they ask for
but there is but this is just a convection
there's no actual connection between slots
and CPUs
it's quite possible to
submit a non-parallel job
that goes often spawns a zillion threads
and sucks up the whole system
in some early versions of grid engine
there actually was up
support for tying slots
for CPU to set it up that
way
there is a sensible implementation for Iraq's
and then things got weirder and weirder is
people try to implement it on other platforms
which had
vastly different
CPU binding semantics
and at this point in time we broke it
on every platform as far as I can tell
also the we decided okay we've got this rapper
let's see what we can do
on in terms of making things work
certainly
we now have have the rapper store allocations in the final system
%uh three and nineteen ninety percent that
allocation I've read them
well we try to do years
find the best fit
fitting set of
adjacent cores
and then if that doesn't work we take orders
to repeat
%um
and until we fix
or until we've got enough slots
the goal is to minimize the fragments we haven't
done any analysis
to determine whether that's actually
an appropriate algorithm
off hand it seems
you'd find another part of a privilege
should forties lay down their arms the US
is
on turns out the FreeBSD, CPU API
and the last one
differ only in very small details
on that
essentially exactly
identical which is
correct in terms pretty semantically
so I think it is of interest to demonstrate
the effectiveness of cebu said they also happen
to demonstrate the %uh
the %uh
rather they probably have
the relevance
it's all of the young box
%um
the and %uh
%uh someone clearly is that
John dalton and backward it's not
our CD set it up for me
shortly before they released
well it's usually is supposed to be shortly
before
and that in essence six two
I will use the simple intervention or so and
greens
program were tested
for instance it
this any play for place
the queen so they can capture each other
on the board
%um
so it's a it's a simple symbol of benchmark
%uh that we ran a a small version of the problem
is our as a measure to man the man to generate
one of the
greta we're close and that we have much longer
some results
so for baseline do it for us
I think the most interesting thing is to do
a slot blot
you see this
some very it's not really very high
not surprising that doesn't really do anything
on accept socks see here
so on
going on what's going on
they don't think in this case for about seven
to one processes and a single
a single assassin process morning
this is the slogans wait wait
and %uh
the standard deviation goes up a bit
to live with a deviation from baseline
the obvious explanation is this
you know were just context switch is a bit
more
and %uh and %uh
because we don't have
CPUs that are doing nothing at all
on this is there some extra load from the system
as well
since the kernel have to run and not contests
have to run
you know if this is a story about maybe a
deposition story
we have people across this is what would some
couples the year
you know we try to run a marathon process
we see a
substantial performance the trees
you know abandon the interest rates that's
a
see if any
the trees
we fired up because the views that
when I saw it
the interesting thing here is to see it
we didn't know statistically significant difference
not between the baseline news with with a
southern cross is it for you see you sense
we don't see this very
which is nice to know that this is it
that's it
we have to we have to see a slight performance
improvement
and %uh
we %uh
we see a reduction in various
hans this issue he says action program performance
even lot of love it
and then you see a vote in the case
it's it's a it's the same
for the opposite the other on process is a
stop on others he years
one interesting side note actually is there
where is the what I was doing some tests early
on
we actually saw
the training base line in the base and a seat
in the senate he just fired off with the original
either of them which
greta
grass seed use your own
he's also if a performance decline
because there's a lot of stuff that ends up
running on see user
which %uh
what led to the year
the for a conservationist you want to allocate
from the large numbers down
so the issue
you see used to not learning the random process
is that it's gone forever we're getting all
the interruptions some architecture's
and it's a way to force the road project
so some conclusions
all I think we have useful prefer concept
of going to be deploying
I was certainly the man with the %uh
memories are seeing
once we have to bring it to you at seven what
definitely be going to see few sets up as
well
so it's a
both includes performance
in the contentious in the and contentious
we would like in the future to do some work
with a personal private superstar
in particular and the really interesting
you know when different
different previous the persons in jails
for to run up for instance up one several
sentences in jail since eleven cents lost
on our allies assistance
there could actually be some really interesting
things there
on in that process which one
we think is actually teach reason except occasions
it's never going to happen only if one takes
we are simply there's another example work
%uh also goes to Tsvangirai who recently
and what if the lights on the same farm workers
seen if we don't have time to implement
all in basic matrix multiplication
relative to current with with current because
%um
previously supervision functionality
that's been reduced the number of GOP entries
on anonymity a stable
and sir
that sort of thing can apply even to allow
me to sing population
a previous the summer winds there
on
Michael what did that work
on the whole on the planet who is leading
uses proliferates
one of the issues we've had is that
you will need to win in the fall
we have reasons to depend on all sorts of
a also to libraries immediate which
you know the vendors like to have them to
do
stupid eight API briefing change is fairly
regularly said
it be nice for users if we can get all the
benefits to cooperate
and you wouldn't have taken operate at their
leisure
so we're hoping to be that in future as well
all would like to see more women Sunday with
type resources
%um
for instance a limiting the amount of
it's it's really what you want you know it's
like you know
all but it's her if you want a place of for
a limit on networking with by a particular
process
all our store almost forced to resign one
and ask how do you classify that traffic with
that
after going to change the current somehow
taking that
it's an interesting challenge
we'd also like to see it could be needed some
you implement something like blacks the irish
job when you're out there
so I was scheduled to just hang out at processes
as part of a job
%uh currently
I've heard it uses a clever but people past
were they out
an extra boost to the process
and they just outrageous troops there
available so they get inherited in the users
can drop them said
thousand track process that it's about what
happened with the correct limits on the number
of groups that can become a real problem
actually for raising questions
argumentative
one quick point
the think it's not interesting you live in
the area and if you're looking for
looking for jobs
we are trying to hire few people it's difficult
to hire good
we do have some some openings and you're looking
for
PSD people in general system ads
people
so questions
%um
I would would expect that to happen
but it's not something that attempted to test
what I would really like is a topology allocator
so that you can request that you know I want
I want to share cache or I don't want to share cache
I want to share memory band width or i want to not share memory band width
actually open MPI of three
on the 1x side have a topology where a rapper for that CPU
functionality
makes it something called %uh
the PLAP
portable lenux
%um
CPU allocator.Is that what
it's actually been
what it would act the act on his part
in essence they have to work around the fact
that there were three standard
there there were three different
currently the eyes for the same siskel
first the EU or takes to get all the letters
to get himself some have used the same number
they're completely about some of these guys
were for routine
when you first saw the application it calls
and this is called a test of figure out which
one it is
whitewater reserve returns depending on what
are you missing and completely evil
I think people support the heat very the eye
and we should have their lives were that
we don't need to do that job because they
didn't make that mistake
so I would like to see it of all its universal
particular
yes larry King
the trick is to do you want to be leaving
it's he's he's a limited application
then with
on
there's no easy limit application
the defense more difficult when you have to
the if you're
the new faces shared between application traffic
%um
they had a fast
getting classifying that is going to treat
you have to take you what the data for particular
to to trace that down through the current
interim I said certainly do
I I am
I I have talked contemplating doing just that
or in fact %uh the other thing we consider
doing
morris a research project that is not practical
jane would be actually help
with would be
independent he lands
because then we could do
things like
the peace process of the lambs' the couldn't
even
sheer at the internet where
once the images in place for instance we will
be able to do that
and that say you know you've got your cases
jurors whatever
on but then we can't win it
we cannot we could raise when did that occur
on can also have
we got of physically isolated we got a lot
of this would have been at work as well
with some analysts which is we can actually
raped women
in this without the switch as well
Bob so that's the first question
we get more and more visible sensitivity cannot
miss foster's
last night the oscars
I'm sorry
we've avoided that problem I think
not allowing it
but is it is a real issue
she's not one we've had to do it
%um
in practice was stuff that sensitive
has handling requirements that you can't touch
the same program without a strong said
you need a mystery
ridiculously aggressive
you need a very close to a new letter to the
end
a ridiculous noted aging process that you
never moved over there
so if I were to do that until we get rid of
that test
just
the witness list
don't get rid of my number-one failure case
of
that would be pretty good but
but havent done that
on
so we we've had occasional problems of NFS overloading
we haven't had real problem
we're all local network is fairly tightly
contained so we haven't had problems with
things
%uh with
you know the server going down for extended
periods and causing everything to hang
it's been more an issue of
I mean there there isn't there's a problem
that Panache is described as in cast
you can take out any NFS
I mean we have the BLueDrat guys come in and the
PGA this stuff multiple ten-gate I said
you know I've got
to do this and they said can we not try this with all your cluster
because if you got
three hundred and fifty
gigabit ethernet interface is going into
the system
even ten gig you can saturate pre-turbulate
so that level
there's an inherent problem
on we need to handle that kind of band width
we've
got to get it a parallel file system
get a cluster
before doing streaming stuff we could go file some loners
anyone else?
thank you